blood pressure is one of the major
cardiovascular risks especially in
relation to stroke essentially if blood
pressure is too high it puts strain on
the walls of Our arteries fortunately
there are extremely simple aids to help
us reduce our blood pressure here now
we're going to discover how black tea
might provide a benefit based on an
analysis that I actually haven't seen
anyone cover before in this analysis
researchers pulled 11 randomized control
trials that measured blood pressure as
well as made sure that each study lasted
a minimum of one week although the
average duration was 6 weeks with some
lasting half a year in addition
participants were instructed to only add
black tea and isolation so not consuming
black tea in conjunction with other
things so then we can isolate the effect
to black tea alone the idea behind black
tea having a blood pressure lowering
effect comes from black tea containing
flat avoids like Thea flavens which I'm
highly tempted to call Tia flavens as
well as kakin these molecules interact
with receptors found on our endothelial
cells so cells that line our blood
vessels and control our blood pressure
when these flavonoids bind specialized
receptors called G protein coupled
receptors and tyrine kinas receptors a
cell signal is translated from the
outside of the cell into to the cell
which ultimately activates a protein
called Enos this Enos protein produces
nitric oxide a molecule that is then
kicked out of the cell and diffuses into
the cells that actually constrict or
loosen the blood vessel nitric oxide is
a well-known vasod dilator so the
presence in these cells called smooth
muscle cells leads to a relaxation of
the blood vessels and the reduction in
blood pressure as the same volume is now
in a larger space that is one primary
mechanism by which flavonoids are
believed to affect blood pressure at
least mechanistically speaking although
there are many other mechanisms like
Scavenging for damaging molecules called
free radicals anyway that's a bit on the
mechanisms but as you know if you've
been following any of my work of late
mechanisms are great but they don't tell
us about the actual intervention in this
case black te
actually if it provides a blood pressure
lowering effect so if we return to set
analysis we can see the effect black tea
consumption has
here we see the uh data on systolic
blood pressure which is the top number
when you get your blood pressure checked
it signifies the highest pressure and we
can see the studies and study arms on
the left side and the numerical results
on the right we also see the weights of
the studies next to that and
if you want a better education on all of
that and what that all means check out
my course on how to analyze and apply
studies to your life for now just know
that the larger the study weight the
more impact it has on the analysis then
there's the diamonds in the middle
they're worth their weight in data even
if they aren't very shiny literally the
zero line indicates no effect and we
have a diamond for each study if they
move to the left that's a blood pressure
lowering effect what we'd expect based
on the mechanisms that we just went over
so some studies lean in that direction
and you know others don't so we can make
sense of the totality of the data by
paying attention to the light gray
diamonds at the bottom as we can see all
the data accounted for there is a blood
pressure lowering effect of black te
regardless of the statistical method
used that's the uh random and fixed
effects that we see there with the
random effects being the more
appropriate considering the Q statistics
there again I'll leave that for my
course to explain so is that it we found
the answer well not quite you hear that
it sounds like a wait a minute it's a
physionic Insider promotion
no cover your ears Run for the hills the
physionic Insiders is my premium
research platform where I'll be
releasing an extended version of this
analysis including more on the types of
black tea consumption more on dosing and
some additional nuances that I won't be
able to cover in the video that you're
watching right now so if you're
interested in getting access to all my
analyses exclusive videos written
research reviews a private Insider
podcast access and joining in live
sessions with yours truly right here
then consider joining the physionic
Insiders the link is in the
description okay I think I think it's
safe to come out jeez that was a close
one there's a few issues with this study
and there's also two things that add a
lot of context to what we just went over
in brief the researchers used a less
rigorous study bias assessment tool
called a deli consensus Which is less
rigorous than some of the others that
are out there that alone tells us that
there's greater risk of bias among
studies the second issue that I'll
mention here is that if we pop open the
data again notice the grai study here
shows up twice unfortunately this is an
improper use of the statistics and the
data because if you open the study it's
the same participants so you're
including their data twice even if the
experiment is different they both
measure blood pressure basically this is
double counting the researchers
mentioned that they account for this by
splitting the weight or impact of the
study in half but this still doesn't
address address the issue properly
there's another problem with this study
that I'll address in the extended
version of the video for the Insiders
because well I don't want to bog this
down with too much statistics let's get
to the uh nuances okay one the
researchers cleverly looked at who gets
the greatest benefit from black tea
consumption and they indicate that
people with high blood pressure
experience the most benefit this is
actually consistent with many other
analyses that we've looked at here on
physionic in fact the Nuance is tied
into this too when considering all the
data the total effect hovers between one
and 2 point drop in systolic or
diastolic blood pressure this is a
pretty small effect but when we consider
that studies included non-hypertensive
and hypertensive participants were all
mixed together it makes one wonder if
the effect might be solely driven by
those with hypertension the researchers
argue that their statistical methods
should have accounted for this but they
acknowledge that the effect is greater
in those with higher blood pressure so
how do we think about all this well the
researchers performed a regression
analysis to identify how different
variables about the people or the
conditions affect the results in fact in
the analysis they indicated that for
every 10o higher blood pressure at
Baseline black tea is linked to about a
onepoint drop in blood pressure since
the lowest blood pressure was 120 units
for for systolic 130 so a 10-point
increase would experience on average a
onepoint reduction from black te
consumption similarly 140 so a 20 point
increase would experience a two point
and so on and so forth and this was done
up to 150 systolic so where does that
leave us what are the main take-home
points here well let me reiterate that
this analysis has some flaws so I'd like
to see a better analysis to be
absolutely sure but as it stands we can
lean toward the take on points that
black tea reduces blood pressure but
minimally black tea is likely a better
go-to if you have high blood pressure
anything from 130 systolic and 85
diastolic and up something like that
black tea likely won't offer much
benefit if you have normal blood
pressure in addition even if you have
high blood pressure black tea will only
provide modest benefits but benefits
nonetheless and simply drinking a tea
not too shabby something that has
greater impact on blood pressure and
cardiovascular health is located right
here see you
[Music]